Finding Aid for Charles W. Brashares papers, 1912-1972
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Charles W. Brashares papers
1912-1972
Brashares, Charles W., 1891-1982.
85815 Aa 2
Pastor of the First Methodist Church of Ann Arbor, Michigan, 1934-1944, later Methodist Episcopal Bishop of the Des Moines, Iowa area and the Chicago, Illinois area. Correspondence, newspaper clippings, and topical files, and miscellanea concerning his; and photographs.
2.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of the Rev. Charles W. Brashares (donor no. 4942 ).
No further additions to the papers expected.
The collection is open to research.
Charles W. Brashares was born March 31, 1891 at Williamsport, Ohio. He attended Ohio Wesleyan, Boston University, Harvard and Cornell, receiving degrees of A.B., D.D., LL.D. He was ordained in the Methodist Episcopal Church in 1917 and served as pastor in Massachusetts, Maine, Ohio, and Michigan from 1917 to 1944. He served in Ann Arbor from 1934 to 1944. He was bishop of the Des Moines area from 1944 to 1952 and bishop of Chicago area since 1952. He died in 1982.
The Brashares collection includes correspondence and topical files relating in part to his pastoral responsibilities, to his work as delegate to the 2nd Assembly of the World Council of Churches, and to his engagement with various social problems. There is some correspondence with G. Bromley Oxnam concerning his appearance before the House Committee on Un-American Activities in 1953.
Subjects:
African Americans--Michigan.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Brashares, Charles W., 1891-1982.; Clergy--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; First Methodist Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Juvenile delinquency--Michigan.; Methodist Episcopal Church.; World Council of Churches.; Methodist Episcopal Church--Michigan--Ann Arbor.MichiganAnn Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Churches.; Clergy.; First Methodist Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Grace Methodist Church (Dayton, Ohio); Methodist churches.; Newton Methodist Church (Newton, Mass.)
Contributors:
Oxnam, G. Bromley (Garfield Bromley), 1891-1963.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  - Undated, 1936-1939 (Box 1)
  - 1940-1946 (Box 1)
  - 1947-1949 (Box 1)
  - 1950-1951 (Box 1)
  - 1952 (Box 1)
  - 1953-1954 (Box 1)
  - 1955, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1956 (Box 1)
  - 1957-1959 (Box 1)
  - 1960-1962 (Box 1)
  - 1963 (Box 1)
  - 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - 1966-1968 (Box 1)
  - 1969 (Box 1)
  - 1970-1972 (Box 1)
- Topical files
  - Bishops, 1948-1964 (Box 1)
  - Chicago, 1945-1964; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1927-1963; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Coordinating Council, 1959-1960 (Box 1)
  - India, 1948-1949 (Box 1)
  - Japan, 1947-1952 (Box 1)
  - Juvenile Delinquency, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Liberia, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Nicholson, Evelyn, 1953-1967 (Box 1)
  - North Central Jurisdictional Conference, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Oxnam, G. Bromley, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Race Relation and Interracial Cooperation, 1942-1963; 5 folders (Box 1)
  - South American Tour, 1956 (Box 2)
  - Town and County Conference, 1951 (Box 2)
  - Training Youth, 1946-1952 (Box 2)
  - Universal Military Training, 1942-1955 (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan, 1937-1940 (Box 2)
  - Vatican Mission, 1951 (Box 2)
  - World Council of Churches, 1954; 5 folders (Box 2)
- Other materials
  - Writings", 1912-1955; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellanea, 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellanea, 8 folders (Box 3)
  - Photographs
    - Portraits (Box 3)
    - Churches: Ann Arbor First United Methodist Church and other churches where Brashares served (Box 3)
    - Groups and meetings (Box 3)